Guide to the Office of the President records, 1795-2007 RG0002
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
- Lloyd H. Elliott records, 1927-1989; 1965-1988; Series 4; 62.5 Linear Feet 39 record center cartons, 8 document boxes
  - Administrative committees and councils, standing and special, 1927-1981; 1960-1972; Series 4 Sub-series 10; 3 Linear Feet 2 record center cartons
    - Research Committee (Standing), 1966-1972 (Box 86, Folder 55)
    - Research Committee (Graduate Council), 1964-1965 (Box 87, Folder 1)
    - Research on Humans Committee (Standing), 1966-1971 (Box 87, Folder 2)
    - Committee on Retirement (Special), 1978-1979 (Box 87, Folder 3)
    - Joint Committee - Review of Health Insurance Coverage (Special), 1978 (Box 87, Folder 4)
    - Science Center Committee (Special), 1963-1966 (Box 87, Folder 5)
    - Committee on Science Center (Ad Hoc), 1962-1963 (Box 87, Folder 6)
    - Science Center Committee Workbook #1, 07/17/1963 (Box 87, Folder 7)
    - Charles E. Smith Center, 1973-1975 (Box 87, Folder 8)
    - Smith Center President's Club, 1975-1976 (Box 87, Folder 9)
    - Sponsored Research Committee (Standing), 1969-1971 (Box 87, Folder 10)
    - Sponsored Research Committee (Special), 1968-1969 (Box 87, Folder 11)
    - Student Court (Special), 1969-1970 (Box 87, Folder 12)
    - Student Financial Aid Committee (Special), 1966 (Box 87, Folder 13)
    - Student Health Services Advisory Committee (Special), 1968-1972 (Box 87, Folder 14)
    - Student Health Services Committee (Special), 1965 (Box 87, Folder 15)
    - Student Life Committee (Special), 1930-1970; 4 folder(s) (Box 87, Folder 16, Folder 17, Folder 18, Folder 19)
    - Committee on Student Loans and Scholarships, 1927-1964 (Box 87, Folder 20)
    - Student Nominating Board, 1976-1977 (Box 87, Folder 21)
    - Student Publications Committee, 1965-1972; 3 folder(s) (Box 87, Folder 22, Folder 23, Folder 24)
    - Student Volunteer Action (Special), 1975-1981 (Box 87, Folder 25)
    - University Bookstore Committee, 1967-1970 (Box 87, Folder 26)
    - University Center Committee, 1965-1969 (Box 87, Folder 27)
    - Westview Apartment House Advisory Committee (Special), 1965 (Box 87, Folder 28)
    - 2121 I Street, N.W., undated (Box 87, Folder 29)
  - Administrative committees, boards and task forces, 1969-1988; 1973-1988; Series 4 Sub-series 11; 3 Linear Feet 2 record center cartons
    The administrative committees, boards and task forces files were transferred to the library by the office of the president in 1999. Formerly accession #768.
    This sub-series is arranged with standing committees first, followed by special, temporary, or ad-hoc groups.
    This sub-series comprises files of materials generated by and about various university-wide committees, boards and task forces. They include correspondence, reports, and other administrative materials. The majority of the materials date from 1973-1988, although they include some records from both before that period.
    - Administrative Standing Committees of the University: Administrative Committees - General Information, undated (Box 88, Folder 1)
    - Administrative Standing Committees of the University: Regulations re Selection of Standing & Special Committees, undated (Box 88, Folder 2)
    - Administrative Standing Committees of the University: Procedures, undated (Box 88, Folder 3)
    - Administrative Standing Committees of the University: Administrative Committees-Opening Meetings, undated (Box 88, Folder 4)
    - Administrative Standing Committees of the University: Requests for Recommendations, undated (Box 88, Folder 5)
    - Administrative Standing Committees of the University: Correspondence-Committees, undated (Box 88, Folder 6)
    - Administrative Standing Committees of the University: Special Committees, 1980-1981 (Box 88, Folder 7)
    - Administrative Standing Committees of the University: Administrative Standing Committees-Lists, 1971 (Box 88, Folder 8)
    - Administrative Standing Committees of the University: Special Committee Lists, 1978 (Box 88, Folder 9)
    - Administrative Standing Committees of the University: Procedures Re Appointment of Special Committees, undated (Box 88, Folder 10)
    - Administrative Standing Committees of the University: Academic Oversight-Committee for Athletics, undated (Box 88, Folder 11)
    - Administrative Standing Committees of the University: Advisory Committee to the Employment Assistance Program, undated (Box 88, Folder 12)
    - Administrative Standing Committees of the University: Campus Security (Standing Committee), undated (Box 88, Folder 13)
    - Administrative Standing Committees of the University: Committee on Coordinated Planning, undated (Box 88, Folder 14)
    - Administrative Standing Committees of the University: Federal Education Allowances (Standing Committee), undated (Box 88, Folder 15)
    - Administrative Standing Committees of the University: Hazardous Materials (Standing Committee), undated (Box 88, Folder 16)
    - Administrative Standing Committees of the University: Institutional Animal Care & Use Committee (Standing Committee, undated (Box 88, Folder 17)
    - Administrative Standing Committees of the University: Formerly Committee on Animal Facilities), undated (Box 88, Folder 18)
    - Administrative Standing Committees of the University: Judicial System (Standing Committee), undated (Box 88, Folder 19)
    - Administrative Standing Committees of the University: Religious Life (Standing Committee), undated (Box 88, Folder 20)
    - Administrative Standing Committees of the University: Public Ceremonies (Standing Committee), undated (Box 88, Folder 21)
    - Administrative Standing Committees of the University: Research (Standing Committee), undated (Box 88, Folder 22)
    - Administrative Standing Committees of the University: Research on Humans (Standing Committee), undated (Box 88, Folder 23)
    - Administrative Standing Committees of the University: Sponsored Research (Standing Committee), undated (Box 88, Folder 24)
    - Administrative Standing Committees of the University: Student-Faculty Committee on Appeals (Standing Committee), undated (Box 88, Folder 25)
    - Administrative Standing Committees of the University: University Bookstore (Standing Committee), undated (Box 88, Folder 26)
    - Administrative Standing Committees of the University: University Parking (Standing Committee), undated (Box 88, Folder 27)
    - Administrative Standing Committees of the University: Educational Opportunity Program, Committee on (Steering), 1979 (Box 88, Folder 28)
    - Administrative Standing Committees of the University: Gerontology (Special), undated (Box 88, Folder 29)
    - Administrative Standing Committees of the University: GW Awards Selection (under Joint Commission), undated (Box 88, Folder 30)
    - Administrative Standing Committees of the University: GW Forum-Editorial Board (Special), undated (Box 88, Folder 31)
    - The Committee to Advise on Policies for Intercollegiate Athletics (Special), undated (Box 89, Folder 1)
    - Joint Committee of Faculty and Students (Special), undated (Box 89, Folder 2)
    - Marvin Center Governing Board (Special), undated (Box 89, Folder 3)
    - Presidential Appeals Board (Special), undated (Box 89, Folder 4)
    - Program Board, Marvin Center (Special), undated (Box 89, Folder 5)
    - Residence Hall Court (Special), undated (Box 89, Folder 6)
    - Smith Center Advisory (Special), undated (Box 89, Folder 7)
    - Student Court (Special), undated (Box 89, Folder 8)
    - Student Traffic Board (Under University Parking) (Special), undated (Box 89, Folder 9)
    - Senate, Ex Officio Appointments, undated (Box 89, Folder 10)
    - Telecommunications Steering Committee (Special), undated (Box 89, Folder 11)
    - Temporary Committees, undated (Box 89, Folder 12)
    - Aids Oversight Committee, undated (Box 89, Folder 13)
    - Ad Hoc Committee on Aids, undated (Box 89, Folder 14)
    - Advisory Committee, University Records Management Program, undated (Box 89, Folder 15)
    - Working Group-Use of GW Facilities & Services by Outside Groups, undated (Box 89, Folder 16)
    - Academic Oversight Committee for Athletics, undated (Box 89, Folder 17)
    - Advisory Committee on the Implementation of the Report of the Commission for the Year 2000 (Box 89, Folder 18)
    - Ad Hoc Compensation Policy Committee, undated (Box 89, Folder 19)
    - Commission for the Year 2000 (Box 89, Folder 20)
    - Drug Committee, undated (Box 89, Folder 21)
    - Evening Committee for International Festival of Cellists, 06/10/1988-06/18/1988 (Box 89, Folder 22)
    - President's Club-Review Committee, undated (Box 89, Folder 23)
    - Retention Committee-Ad Hoc, undated (Box 89, Folder 24)
    - University Seminar on Ancient Mediterranean, undated (Box 89, Folder 25)
    - University Seminar on Socio-Economics, undated (Box 89, Folder 26)
    - Space Committee, Ad Hoc, undated (Box 89, Folder 27)
    - Task Force on Registration-Ad Hoc, undated (Box 89, Folder 28)
    - Wellness Committee-Ad Hoc Ad Hoc Committee-TIAA/CREF, undated (Box 89, Folder 29)
    - Ad Hoc Committee-Impact of Student Financial Aid on Ability to Recruit and Retain Students, undated (Box 89, Folder 30)
    - Ad Hoc Committee to Study Programs re Washington, undated (Box 89, Folder 31)
    - 2000 Pennsylvania-Front Door Committee, undated (Box 89, Folder 32)
    - Luther Rice Home Site (Temporary), undated (Box 89, Folder 33)
    - Search Committee for Dean of the Division of Continuing Education, undated (Box 89, Folder 34)
    - Ad Hoc-Special Collections Review Committee, undated (Box 89, Folder 35)
    - University Librarian Search Committee, undated (Box 89, Folder 36)
    - Search Committee for Vice President of Development, undated (Box 89, Folder 37)
    - Committee on Service Awards Program (Ad Hoc), 1982 (Box 89, Folder 38)
    - Middle States Asssociation-Steering Committee for Periodic Review Report, undated (Box 89, Folder 39)
    - Director of Men's Athletics-Search Committee for, undated (Box 89, Folder 40)
    - Smith Center-Search Committee for Trustees' Retreat, undated (Box 89, Folder 41)
    - Standing and Special Administrative Committees-Sample Letters of Appointment, undated (Box 89, Folder 42)
  - Selected special events files, 1976-1988; Series 4 Sub-series 12; 0.5 Linear Feet 1 document box
    The selected special events files were received from the office of the president in 1999. Formerly accession #768.
    The files in this sub-series are arranged chronologically by the date of the event.
    This sub-series comprises files of information about selected special events attended by President Elliott. They include materials such as correspondence, programs, text of speeches, and planning documents.
    - Trustees' Dinner honoring the Elliotts retirement, 05/19/1988 (Box 90, Folder 1)
    - Dinner for Vice President William P. Smith, 06/21/1988 (Box 90, Folder 2)
    - Dedication of 2000 Pennsylvania Avenue, N.W., 10/19/1983 (Box 90, Folder 3)
    - Dedication of The Robert H. and Clarice Smith Hall of Art-Luncheon, 10/20/1983 (Box 90, Folder 4)
    - Dedication and Dinner-Benjamin T. Rome Hall, 01/23/1984 (Box 90, Folder 5)
    - 10th Anniversary of Gelman Library & Millionth Volume Celebration, 03/26/1984-04/02/1984 (Box 90, Folder 6)
    - Lerner Dedication & Dinner, 04/26/1984 (Box 90, Folder 7)
    - Jacob Burns Dinner and Dedication, 10/18/1984 (Box 90, Folder 8)
    - Phillips Hall Dedication and Dinner, 06/03/1986 (Box 90, Folder 9)
    - Smith Center 10th Anniversary Reception and Buffet, 06/30/1986 (Box 90, Folder 10)
    - Gelman Library Naming, 05/14/1980 (Box 90, Folder 11)
    - Bloedorn Ceremony, 11/12/1980 (Box 90, Folder 12)
    - F Street Club Dinner-Chief Justice Burger, 07/22/1981 (Box 90, Folder 13)
    - Presentation Ceremonyk: Portrait of Burgess Allison by Gilbert Stuart, 01/28/1983 (Box 90, Folder 14)
    - Reception at GW Club honoring Dr. Alpert's retirement, 06/22/1983 (Box 90, Folder 15)
    - Reception and Dinner-Medical Center, Red China Guests, 07/17/1974 (Box 90, Folder 16)
    - Dinner-Ambassador of Iran, 11/26/1974 (Box 90, Folder 17)
    - Party-George Walls (President's Driver), 06/17/1975 (Box 90, Folder 18)
    - Charles E. Smith Dinner, 06/02/1976 (Box 90, Folder 19)
    - Iranian Luncheon-GWU, 06/17/1976 (Box 90, Folder 20)
    - Iranian Dinner-Iranian Dinner, 07/27/1976 (Box 90, Folder 21)
  - Middle States Accreditation Reports and Background Papers, 1954, 1966-1987; Series 4 Sub-series 13; 3.875 Linear Feet 4 document boxes, 1.25 record center cartons
    The Middle States evaluation reports and background papers were sent to the library by the office of the president around 1980.
    The background papers are arranged alphabetically by university unit; the remainder of the sub-series does not appear to be arranged in any particular order.
    This sub-series comprises materials created as part of the process of accreditation by the Middle States Commission on Higher Education. It includes background reports on the various university units prepared in advance of the 1967 accreditation review, as well as progress reports, self-study reports, and visit reports from 1954, 1967-1969, 1976-1977 and 1987, and some correspondence related to the accreditation process.
    - Middle States Association Progress Report, 1969 (Box 91, Folder 1)
    - Middle States Association Progress Report, Summary of Evaluation Report, 1967-1969 (Box 91, Folder 2)
    - Middle States Association Reevaluation of G.W.U., 1967 (Box 91, Folder 3)
    - Middle States Association Evaluation, 1966-1967 (Box 91, Folder 4)
    - Evaluation Report of G.W.U. for the Comission of institutions of higher learning, undated (Box 91, Folder 5)
    - MSA Evaluation of G.W.U., Progress Report, 1966-1967, 1969 (Box 91, Folder 6)
    - Background Papers: Administration and Organization, undated (Box 92, Folder 1)
    - Background Papers: Board of Trustees, 1966 (Box 92, Folder 2)
    - Background Papers: Admissions, 1966 (Box 92, Folder 3)
    - Background Papers: Basic Considerations Underlying an Academic Plan, September 30, 1965 (Box 92, Folder 4)
    - Background Papers: Columbian College, 1966 (Box 92, Folder 5)
    - Background Papers: Consortium, 1965-1966 (Box 92, Folder 6)
    - Background Papers: Dean of Women, 1966 (Box 92, Folder 7)
    - Background Papers: Education, Report to NCATE, 1965 (Box 92, Folder 8)
    - Background Papers: School of Engineering, 1966 (Box 92, Folder 9)
    - Background Papers: Financing, 1969 (Box 92, Folder 10)
    - Background Papers: School of Government and Business Administration, 1966 (Box 92, Folder 11)
    - Background Papers: Graduate Council, 1966-1967 (Box 92, Folder 12)
    - Background Papers: Health Services, 1966 (Box 92, Folder 13)
    - Background Papers: Library, 1965-1968; 2 folder(s) (Box 92, Folder 14, Folder 15)
    - Background Papers: School of Medicine, undated (Box 93, Folder 1)
    - Background Papers: Men's Athletics, undated (Box 93, Folder 2)
    - Background Papers: Middle States Association of Colleges and Secondary Schools, undated (Box 93, Folder 3)
    - Background Papers: E.K. Morris, undated (Box 93, Folder 4)
      This folder is missing.
    - Background Papers: National Law Center, undated (Box 93, Folder 5)
    - Background Papers: School of Public Law and International Affairs, undated; 2 folder(s) (Box 93, Folder 6, Folder 7)
    - Background Papers: Resources, undated (Box 93, Folder 8)
    - Background Papers: Senate, undated (Box 93, Folder 9)
    - Background Papers: Sino-Soviet Institute, undated (Box 93, Folder 10)
    - Background Papers: Sponsered Research, undated (Box 93, Folder 11)
    - Background Papers: Students (Foreign), undated (Box 93, Folder 12)
    - Background Papers: Students Intermural Programs, undated (Box 93, Folder 13)
    - Background Papers: Students Orientation, undated (Box 93, Folder 14)
    - Background Papers: Students Publications, undated (Box 93, Folder 15)
    - Background Papers: Summer Sessions, undated (Box 93, Folder 16)
    - Background Papers: Treasurer, undated (Box 93, Folder 17)
    - Background Papers: University Senate Annual and Committe, undated (Box 93, Folder 18)
    - Background Papers: Organization and Administration, undated (Box 93, Folder 19)
    - Background Papers: Chapter 8, undated (Box 93, Folder 20)
    - Background Papers: Outcomes, undated (Box 93, Folder 21)
    - Mailing List - MSA Report, undated (Box 93, Folder 22)
    - Middle States Documents, undated (Box 93, Folder 23)
    - MSA Visiting Team, undated (Box 93, Folder 24)
    - Final Evaluation, undated (Box 93, Folder 25)
    - Correspondence - Faculty and Administration, undated (Box 94, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence - Board of Trustees, undated (Box 94, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence - University Senate, undated (Box 94, Folder 3)
    - Middle States Accreditation Reports and Supporting Documentation, 1954, 1966 (Box 94)
    - Middle States Association of Colleges and Schools Evaluation Report, 1967, 02/12/1967-02/15/1967 (Box 95, Folder 1)
    - Middle States Association of Colleges and Schools Progress Report, 1969, 09/26/1969-10/01/1969 (Box 95, Folder 2)
    - Middle States Association of Colleges and Schools Report, 1976, 12/1976 (Box 95, Folder 3)
    - Middle States Association of Colleges and Schools Self Study Report, 1977, 1976-1977 (Box 95, Folder 4)
    - Middle States Association of Colleges and Schools Self Study Report, 1987, 11/20/1987 (Box 95, Folder 5)
    - Middle States Association of Colleges and Schools - Accreditation, 12/1976-01/1983 (Box 96)
      The box contains extra copies of the University's report to the Middle States dated December 1976 and a copy of the University's Periodic Review Report to the Commission, dated January 1983.
  - Miscellaneous files, Series 4 Sub-series 14; 1.125 Linear Feet 0.75 record center carton
    This sub-series is not arranged in any particular order, although the similar files have been kept together.
    This sub-series includes materials that are not part of one of the clearaly-identifiable file sets created by the office of the president. Some of them, such as the materials about Elliott's selection, appear to have originated with the office of the president but the manner in which they came to the archives has been subsequently lost. Other files appeara to have been collected and organized by someone outside of the president's office, such as a librarian or archivist. This sub-series includes the 1987 publication, "The Elliott Years," which served as a tribute to Elliott's presidency, as well as the 1987 annual report.
    - Extra Commencement Programs, 1976-05/03/1981 (Box 54)
    - Annual Report, "The Elliott Years", 1987 (Box 95, Folder 6)
    - Publication, "The Elliott Years", circa 1987 (Box 95, Folder 6)
    - Committee to Select a New President, undated (Box 95, Folder 7)
    - Board of Trustees, undated (Box 95, Folder 8)
    - Personal & Confidential-O.S. Colclough, undated (Box 95, Folder 9)
    - Lloyd H. Elliott-Appointment as President, undated (Box 95, Folder 10)
    - Memorandum Re Presidency of the University, 05/1965 (Box 95, Folder 11)
    - Congratulatory Letters, undated (Box 95, Folder 12)
    - Lloyd H. Elliott-Congratulatory Messages, undated (Box 95, Folder 13)
    - Letters of Congratulations re Appointment as President of The George Washington University, undated (Box 95, Folder 14)
    - The George Washington University-Materials Re, undated (Box 95, Folder 15)
    - Confidential Envelope: Correspondence from Deans re Candidates for Presidency of the University (Except Dr. Elliott), 1965 (Box 95, Folder 16)
    - Presidents--Selection of University President, 1964-1965 (Box 95, Folder 17)
    - Presidents--Selection of University President, 01/1965-08/1965 (Box 95, Folder 18)
    - Presidents--Elliott, Lloyd--News clippings of early days at GW, undated (Box 95, Folder 19)
    - Presidents--Elliott, Lloyd--Correspondence, invitations, 1966-1988 (Box 95, Folder 20)
    - Presidents--Elliott, Lloyd--White House invitations, 1981-1985 (Box 95, Folder 21)
    - Presidents--Elliott, Lloyd, 02/04/1966-03/24/1988 (Box 95, Folder 22)
    - President's Newsletter, 1967-1969 (Box 95, Folder 23)
- Stephen J. Trachtenberg records, 1984-2008; 1988-2007; Series 5; 199 Linear Feet 132 record center cartons, 1 document box, 2 oversize folders, 1 slim document box, 2 flat boxes
  The contents of this series are closed for 50 years from the date of creation, with the exception of the Trachtenberg writings sub-series and the Miscellaneous sub-series, both of which are open for use. Permission to use restricted materials may be obtained from the office of the president; please contact archives@gwu.edu to facilitate permission.
  Except as noted in sub-series descriptions below, the contents of this series were transferred to the archives by the office of the president in 2008 and 2012.
  This series is arranged in 19 subseries: 9 subseries of alphabetical correspondence files, 2 subseries of correspondence with GW administrators, 1 subseries of travel files, 1 subseries of writings by or about President Trachtenberg, 1 subseries of agreements and memoranda of understanding, 1 subseries of miscellaneous files, 1 subseries of search files, legal files, and accreditation files, 1 subseries of Vice Presidents' reports, 1 series of video recordings, 1 series of honorary degrees, photographs, and other materials.
  Stephen Joel Trachtenberg was president of The George Washington University from 1988 to 2007. He came to GW from the University of Hartford, where he had been President for eleven years. Before assuming the presidency of Hartford, Trachtenberg served for eight years at Boston University as Vice President for Academic Services and Academic Dean of the College of Liberal Arts. Earlier, in Washington, D.C., he was a Special Assistant for two years to the U.S. Education Commissioner, Department of Health, Education and Welfare. He has been an attorney with the U.S. Atomic Energy Commission and a legislative aide to former Indiana Congressman John Brademas.
  In 1989, President Trachtenberg created the Office of Campus Life and made the commitment to offer programs and services "to enhance the personal, professional, social and cultural development of the University community." Other accomplishments include the remodeling of Lisner Auditorium and the campus bookstore, new seating for the Smith Center, the development of Francis Field for GW Athletics, and the creation of a 24-hour reading room within Gelman Library.
  Stephen Joel Trachtenberg became GW President in 1988, replacing Lloyd Elliott. The School of Public and International Affairs was renamed the Elliott School of International Affairs.President Trachtenberg affirmed his commitment to the importance of teaching at the University with the establishment of the University Teaching Center. He also created the 21st Century Scholars program, allowing high school students within the District of Columbia to attend the University and participate in aspects of campus life. President Trachtenberg has endorsed and advanced policies designed to increase excellence in research, graduate and undergraduate liberal arts education, and budgetary stability and quality management for the University. Between August 28, 1995, and May 19, 1996, the University celebrated its 175th Anniversary.